A Guide to the Edgar B. Young papers FA109
Rockefeller Archive Center
Edgar B. Young papers
1952-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Young, Edgar B.
Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison) (1906-1978)
Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts
Japan Society. (New York, N.Y.)
FA109
28.15 Cubic Feet 71 letter document boxes, 1 legal document box, 1 letter document box (wide), and 1 flat file folder
Arrangement note
The Edgar B. Young papers are arranged into three series:
Series 1 - Lincoln Center, Inc. (1952-1980) Series 2 - Japan Society (1973-1978) Series 3 - Photographs
The material within each series is further divided in subseries arranged alphabetically by subject. The material within each subseries is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Biographical/Historical note
Edgar B. Young, a staff associate of John D. Rockefeller 3rd (JDR 3rd), played a vital role in the creation and early administration of Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts.
Young was born April 27, 1908, in Anderson, Indiana. His academic credentials include an A.B. from DePauw University (1929) and graduate work at the London School of Economics (Economics 1931), the University of Pennsylvania (Economics 1933), and American University (Public Administration 1935).
Prior to his employment as a Rockefeller family associate, Young held several administrative positions in the U. S. Employment Service (1934-1939) and the U. S. Bureau of the Budget (1939-1941). He also served as an Assistant to the Executive Director of the Port of New York Authority (1945-1946). From 1946 to 1949, Young began his service to the Rockefeller family as a staff associate of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Then in 1949, he became the full-time staff associate for JDR 3rd and served in that capacity throughout the time period of the balance of the records documented in this collection.
Young's career closely mirrors the interests and activities of JDR 3rd. In the early 1950s, JDR 3rd devoted much of his energy to the promotion of a greater cultural and educational exchange between Asia and western societies, most notably the United States. These activities centered around the revitalization of the Japan Society, for which Young was appointed Secretary in 1952, and the creation of the Asia Society, for which Young was appointed Secretary upon its founding in 1956.
Young was actively involved in the Lincoln Center project from its origin, participating in many of the early discussions while JDR 3rd served on the Exploratory Committee for a Musical Arts Center. After incorporation, Young became Lincoln Center's Secretary (1956-1962) and JDR 3rd became its first President (June 22, 1956-1961). Rockefeller was succeeded as President by General Maxwell Taylor on January 4, 1961. Following Taylor's resignation to accept a position as military advisor for President John F. Kennedy, Young served as the Acting President of Lincoln Center from June 26 to December 31, 1961. At that time, William Schuman was named the third President of Lincoln Center (1961-1968) and Young was subsequently appointed Executive Vice President (1962-1965) and Chairman of the Building Committee (1961-1971). Young also often served as a member of both the Executive and Education Committees at various points throughout his tenure with Lincoln Center.
Scope and Contents note
Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts is a nonprofit institution dedicated to fostering the arts of opera, music, dance, drama, and arts education. Its objective is not only to exist as a physical place where the arts are created and performed, but also to promote and facilitate access to the arts to as wide an audience as possible.
The Edgar B. Young collection documents Lincoln Center as a project fueled by the work and vision of volunteers and the non-profit sector of the economy. It serves as a model of successful urban renewal and collaboration between the private sector and various agencies of all levels of government.
The birth of Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts developed from the convergence of three independent actions. First was the availability of land. In 1954, the New York City Committee on Slum Clearance (under the chairmanship of Robert Moses and Mayor Robert Wagner) designated a 17-block area of Manhattan between West 62nd and West 70th Streets for redevelopment. Once the appropriate city government approvals were obtained, this became the Lincoln Square Urban Renewal Project (with Lincoln Square as the intersection of Broadway and Columbus Avenue). Second and third, two major New York art associations, the Metropolitan Opera Association and the Philharmonic-Symphony Society, were both actively and independently looking for new homes. Both organizations had independently come to the conclusion that building a new home to fit their custom specifications and acoustic requirements, rather than becoming a tenant in an existing structure, was essential for their performers and the long term existence and growth of their organizations.
The catalyst for the convergence of these independent activities into one interrelated project was Wallace K. Harrison who had been asked to serve as the design architect for both the new Metropolitan Opera House and the Philharmonic Hall project. Harrison also had a long standing relationship with various New York City government officials as well as the Rockefeller family. Harrison met with John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Chair of the Board of the Rockefeller Foundation at the time, and Young to discuss the dilemma confronting the Metropolitan Opera and the Philharmonic as well as possible solutions. Young and JDR 3rd were interested in further participation and soon after met with other prominent art administrators including Lincoln Kirstein (Managing Director of the New York City Ballet) and William Shuman (President of the Juilliard School). On the invitation of Charles Spofford (Metropolitan Opera Association Executive Committee Chairman), JDR 3rd attended informal meetings with many of these same men, leading to the establishment of the Exploratory Committee for a Musical Arts Center with the objective of defining a common mission and building a performing arts center. This committee eventually led to the incorporation of Lincoln Center in 1956 and, after decades of planning, designing and redesigning, construction and reconstruction, the opening and operation of the nation's largest performing arts complex.
The Edgar B. Young Papers document Young's professional career with Lincoln Center and, to a much lesser extent, the Japan Society. This is not a collection of his personal papers. Due to Young's extensive experience in a wide variety of Lincoln Center positions and activities, this collection documents all aspects of the Lincoln Center project including the origin of Lincoln Center, Inc.; the planning, construction, and completion of each of the original buildings; early administration and operations; constituent relations; fundraising; financial administration; public relations; and the adoption of various sponsored programs beyond the original scope of its mandate such as the Lincoln Center Student Program, the Lincoln Center Film Festival, and sponsorship of the New York World's Fair.
Related Archival Materials note
Related Collections at the Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Series E - Cultural Interests Boxes 36-43 on Lincoln Center.
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Series P - Ann C. Whitman - Politics Box 23, Folder 522 on E. B. Young and the New York State Theater Construction
John D. Rockefeller 3rd Papers Series 1 - Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller Files Subseries 3 - Asian Interests, Boxes 35-56 Subseries 4 - Lincoln Center, Boxes 57-79 Series 3 - Office and Home Files Subseries 3 - Philanthropy and Public Interests, Box 47, Folders 285-290 on Lincoln Center Subseries 5 - Asian Interests, Boxes 75-80
Rockefeller Family Archives, Record Group 13 - Public Relations Various press releases and published articles
Rockefeller Foundation records, Record Group 1.2 - Projects, Series 200R - United States - Arts and Humanities Boxes 364-369, Folders 3288-3321 - Lincoln Center Board of Directors Minutes and Reports, 1950s-1960s
Malcolm Wilson Papers, World's Fair Files, Boxes 8-9, Folders 224-263
Young, Edgar B., "Lincoln Center: The Building of An Institution." New York: New York University Press, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Urban renewal; Japan; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); Arts; Philanthropy; Performing arts
- Lincoln Center, Inc., 1952-1980 (1956-1976); 1956-1976; 1; 26.48 Cubic Feet 68 letter document boxes, 1 legal document box, and 1 flat file folder; 69 Boxes 27.6 cubic feet
  Arrangement note
  This series encompasses the overwhelming majority of the collection and is arranged into 11 subseries, each of which is organized alphabetically by folder title:
  Subseries 1 - Administration Subseries 2 - Art Subseries 3 - Building Operations Subseries 4 - Constituent Relations Subseries 5 - Education Subseries 6 - Financial Administration Subseries 7 - Fundraising Subseries 8 - Kirstein, Lincoln Subseries 9 - Planning and Construction Subseries 10 - Public Relations Subseries 11 - Working Files
  - Administration, 1956-1980; 1
    Scope and Contents note
    The material presented here includes complete sets of the Board of Directors (1956-1978) and Executive Committee (1961-1978) meeting minutes, as well as the by-laws and certificate of incorporation for Lincoln Center, Inc. It is a loose federation of constituent institutions with each constituent retaining absolute artistic and financial autonomy for its organization. The primary relationship between Lincoln Center, Inc. and its constituents is that of landlord to tenant, with Lincoln Center, Inc. holding the ownership of all buildings, structures, common spaces and pledging to act in the common interest of all parties.
    This subseries also contains background material for Edgar B. Young's 1970 summary report which details the capital funding from incorporation in 1956 through initial building completion in 1969. Although this subseries does contain some financial policy and finance related records, those interest in more detailed financial matters may wish to consult Subseries 6 - Financial Administration.
    - Administrative Committee, 1969-June 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Administrative Committee, August-December 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Administrative Committee, January-March 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Administrative Committee, June-September 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Administrative Committee, October 1972-September 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Advertising - Vitrine Displays, 1963-1966 (1973) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, 1966-June 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, 1968-June 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany - Traffic Analysis, November 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, January-April 14, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, April 26 - December 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, February-May 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Board of Directors - Correspondence and Miscellany, June-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - Conferences, February 17-18 and June 7, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, June-December 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-June 1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, July-December 1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-May 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, June-December 1958 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-April 1959 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May-September 1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, October-December 1959 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-April 1960 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May-September 1960 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, October-December 1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-May 1961 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, June-December 1961 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1970-1971 (1979) (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1972 (1979) (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, 1973 (1979) (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-March 1974 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-March 1975 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May-December 1974 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May-September 1975 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January-April 1976 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May 1976 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, June-October 1976 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, January 1977 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May 1977 (1979) (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, September 1977 (1979) (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, December 1977 (1979) (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, February-March 1978 (1979) (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, May-July 1978 (1979) (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Board of Directors and Members Meetings Minutes - General Files, September-December 1978 (1979) (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Bookings, 1959-1961 (1971) (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - By-Laws and Certificate of Incorporation, 1956-1957 (1971) (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - By-Laws and Certificate of Incorporation, 1959-January 1961 (1971) (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - By-Laws and Certificate of Incorporation, March 1961-1970 (1971) (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - By-Laws and Certificate of Incorporation, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, January-July 1961 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, August-December 1961 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971), February-July 1966 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971), September 1966-February 1967 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971), March-December 1967 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971), January-October 1968 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971), November 1968-September 1969 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971), December 1969-November 1970 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes (Reviewed by S.B., 1971) (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, January-April 1973 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, May-December 1973 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, January-April 1974 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, May-October 1974 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, January-March 1975 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, October-November 1975 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, January-February 1976 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, April-September 1976 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, October-November 1976 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, January-April 1977 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, May-October 1977 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, November 1977 (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, December 1977 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, April-September 1978 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Executive Committee Meetings Minutes, October-November 1978 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Financial and Policy Problems, 1965-October 1966 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Financial and Policy Problems, November-December 1966 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Financial and Policy Problems, January-May 1967 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - Financial and Policy Problems, June-August 1967 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Financial and Policy Problems, September-December 1967, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - Key People - Allen, Reginald, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Key People - Allen, Reginald, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 93a)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2027; Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2030
    - Key People - Mazzola, John W., 1962 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - Key People - Nelson, Otto L., Jr. - General, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - Key People - Schuman, William, 1961-1976 (Box 10, Folder 96)
    - Key People - Schuman, William, 1961-1976 (Box 10, Folder 96a)
      Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2031; Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2035; Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2038
    - Key People - Spofford, Charles M., 1959 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Key People - Taylor, Maxwell D. - General - Organization Queries and Replies, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Key People - Taylor, Maxwell D., 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Key People - Taylor, Maxwell D., 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 99a)
      Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2030; Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2032
    - Organization of Staff - General Files, circa 1956-1980 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Organization of Staff - Organizational Charts, 1961-1965 (1973) (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - Policy Planning Committee, January-March 10, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - Policy Planning Committee, March 20-May 1969 (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Presidency of Lincoln Center, June 1969 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Public Spaces and Revenue-Producing Facilities, 1958-1960 (1971) (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Report - Background Material on 1970 Summary, 1955-October 1957 (1976) (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Report - Background Material on 1970 Summary, December 1957-January 1959 (1976) (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - Report - Background Material on 1970 Summary, February 1959-1962 (1976) (Box 11, Folder 108)
    - Report - Background Material on 1970 Summary, 1963-September 1965 (1976) (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - Report - Background Material on 1970 Summary, November 1965-1969 (1976) (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - Restaurants and Refreshment Facilities, 1958-1965 (1972) (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - Ticket Sales, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - Traffic, 1958-1963 (1971) (Box 11, Folder 113)
    - Traffic, 1965-1969 (1971) (Box 11, Folder 114)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also RAC Photograph Collection, Series 1073, Box 1, Folder 1.
  - Art, 1960-1972; 2
    This subseries documents various art-related grants and the subsequent art acquisitions, including Alexander Calder's stabile "Guichet" and Henry Moore's "Reclining Figure." The largest single grant to Lincoln Center for visual arts was given by the Albert A. List Foundation in 1961 and included funds to commission posters for special events.
    - Arts and Acquisitions Policy, 1960-1962 (1973) (Box 11, Folder 115)
      Architectural material has been removed and is housed separately.
    - Scan of Lincoln Center Floor plan., 1961 April; ARCHITECTURAL DRAWING (Quantity 1) (Drawer D 14, Folder 1)
      Separated Materials note
      Separated from Series 1.2 Art, Box 11, Folder 115
    - Arts and Acquisitions Policy, 1962-1964 (1973) (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - Arts and Acquisitions Policy, 1963-1965 (1973) (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - Arts and Acquisitions Policy, 1965-1972 (1973) (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - Arts and Acquisitions Policy, 1966-1971 (1973) (Box 11, Folder 119)
    - Buildings - Juilliard - Sculpture - Nagare, Masayuki - Untitled, 1967-1968 (1970) (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Floor plan for Sculptures at Julliard School of Music., 1968 January 18; ARCHITECTURAL DRAWING (Quantity 1) (Drawer D 14, Folder 1)
      Separated from Series 1.2 Art, Box 12, Folder 120
    - Buildings - Juilliard - Sculpture - Nagare, Masayuki - Untitled, 1969-January 1970 (1970) (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Buildings - Juilliard - Sculpture - Nagare, Masayuki - Untitled, February-May 1970 (1970) (Box 12, Folder 122)
      See also RAC Photograph Collection, Series 1073, Box 1, Folder 2.
    - Buildings - Juilliard - Works of Art, 1969-1970 (1973) (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Buildings - Metropolitan Opera - Sculpture - Lehmbruck, Wilhelm - "Kneeling Woman", 1961-1967 (1971) (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Buildings - Metropolitan Opera - Works of Art, 1960-1966 (1971) (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Buildings - New York State Theater - Works of Art (Acquisitions, etc.), 1962-April 1964 (1971) (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Buildings - New York State Theater - Works of Art (Acquisitions, etc.), August-December 1964 (1971) (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - Buildings - New York State Theater - Works of Art (Acquisitions, etc.), 1965-1968 (1971) (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Buildings - Philharmonic Hall - Works of Art (Acquisitions, etc.), 1962-1965 (1971) (Box 12, Folder 129)